<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The apology of Sr. Francis Bacon, Kt. in certain imputations concerning the late Earl of Essex written to the Right Honourable his very good Lord the Earl of Devonshire, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.</title>
            <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27214</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09717749</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09717749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44030</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28017)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44030)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1348:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The apology of Sr. Francis Bacon, Kt. in certain imputations concerning the late Earl of Essex written to the Right Honourable his very good Lord the Earl of Devonshire, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
                  <author>Devonshire, Charles Blount, Earl of, 1563-1606.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.G. &amp; B.G. for William Lee,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: The Lord Bacon's apology touching the late Earl of Essex.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1566-1601.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44030:1"/>
            <p>THE APOLOGY OF S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> FRANCIS BACON K<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> In certain Imputations concerning the late Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WRITTEN To the Right Honourable his very good Lord, the Earl of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. G.</hi> &amp; <hi>B. G.</hi> for <hi>William Lee,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the Turks-Head in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Fetter-Lane,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:44030:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44030:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable his very good Lord, the Earl of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may pleaſe your good Lordſhip: I cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and ought to be ſenſible of the wrong which I ſuſtain in common ſpeech, as if I had been falſe, or unthankful to that noble, but unfortunate Earl, the Earl of <hi>Eſſex:</hi> and for ſatisfying the vulgar ſort, I do not ſo much regard it; though I love a good name, but yet as an handmaid, and attendant of honeſty and vertue. For I am of his opinion that ſaid pleaſantly, <hi>That it was a ſhame to him that was a Suiter to the Miſtriſs, to make love to the Waiting woman;</hi> and therefore to woe or court common fame otherwiſe then it followeth on honeſt courſes, I for my part, find not my ſelf fit nor diſpoſed. But on the other ſide, there is no worldly thing that concerneth my ſelf which I hold more dear, than the good opinion of certain perſons; amongſt which there is none I would more willingly give ſatisfaction unto, then to your Lordſhip. Firſt, becauſe you loved my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and therefore will not be partial towards me; which is part of that I deſire, next, becauſe it hath ever pleaſed you to ſhew your ſelf to me an honorable friend; and ſo no baſeneſs in me to ſeek to ſatisfie you: and laſtly becauſe I know your Lordſhip is exccel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently grounded in the true rules and habits of duties and moralities; which muſt be they which ſhall decide this matter: wherein (my Lord) my defence needeth to be but ſimple and brief: namely, that whatſoever I did concerning that action and proceeding, was done in my duty and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the Queen and the State; in which I would not ſhew my ſelf falſe-hearted, nor faint-hearted, for any mans ſake living. For every honeſt man that hath his heart well planted, will forſake his King, rather than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake God; and forſake his friend, rather than forſake his King; and yet wil forſake any earthly commodity, yea, and his own life in ſome caſes, rather than forſake his friend. I hope the world hath not forgotten theſe degrees elſe the heathen ſaying; <hi>Amicus uſque ad aras,</hi> ſhall judge them.</p>
            <p>And if any man ſhall ſay, I did officiouſly intrude my ſelf into that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, becauſe I had no ordinary place; the like may be ſaid of all the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in effect that paſſed the hands of the learned Councel, either of State or Revenues theſe many years, wherein I was continually uſed. For, as your Lordſhip may remember, the Queen knew her ſtrength ſo well, as ſhe looked her word ſhould be a warrant; and after the manner of the choiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Princes before her, did not always tye her truſt to place, but did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time divide private favour from office. And I for my part, though I was not ſo unſeen in the world, but I knew the condition was ſubject to envy and peril; yet becauſe I knew again ſhe was conſtant in her favours, and made an end were ſhe began, and eſpecially, becauſe ſhe upheld me with extraordinary acceſs, and other demonſtrations of confidence and grace, I reſolved to indure it, in expectation of better. But my ſcope and deſire is,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44030:3"/>
that your Lordſhip would be pleaſed to have the honourable patience, to know the truth, in ſome particularity, of all that paſſed in this cauſe, wherein I had any part, that you may perceive how honeſt a heart I ever bear to my Soveraign, and to my Country, and to that Noble man, who had ſo well deſerved of me, and ſo well accepted of my deſervings; whoſe fortune I cannot remember without much grief. But for any action of mine towards him, there is nothing that paſſed me in my life time, that cometh to my remembrance with more clearneſs, and leſs check of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: for it will appear to your Lordſhip, that I was not only not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> but that I did occupy the utmoſt of my wits, and adventure my fortune with the Queen to have reintegrated his, and ſo continued faithfully and induſtriouſly, till his laſt fatal impatience (for ſo I will call it) after which day there was not time to work for him though the ſame, my affection, when it could not work on the ſubject proper) went to the next, with no ill effect towards ſome others, who I think do rather not know it, than not acknowledge it. And this I will aſſure your Lordſhip, I will leave nothing untold, that is truth for any enemy that I have to adde; and on the other ſide, I muſt reſerve much which makes for me, in many reſpects of duty, which I eſteem above my credit: and what I have here ſet down to your Lordſhip, I proteſt, as I hope to have any part in <hi>God</hi>'s favour, is true.</p>
            <p>It is well known, how I did many years ſince dedicate my travels and ſtudies, to the uſe and (as I may tearm it) ſervice of my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> which I proteſt before God, I did not, making election of him as the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt mean of mine own advancement, but out of the humor of a man, that ever, from the time I had any uſe of reaſon (whether it were reading upon good books, or upon the example of a good Eather, or by nature) I loved my Country more than was anſwerable to my fortune, and I held at that time, my Lord to be the fitter inſtrument to do good to the State: and therefore I applied my ſelf to him, in a manner which I think hapneth rarely among men: for I did not only labour carefully and induſtriouſly in that he ſet me about, whether it were matter of advice or otherwiſe, but neglecting the Queens ſervice, mine own fortune, and in a ſort my vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I did nothing but adviſe and ruminate with my ſelf to the beſt of my underſtanding, propoſitions and memorials, of any thing that might concern his Lordſhips honour, fortune, or ſervice. And when not long after I entred into this courſe, my Brother Mr. <hi>Anthony Bacon</hi> came from beyond the Seas, being a Gentleman whoſe ability the world taketh knowledge of for matters of State, ſpecially forraign, I did likewiſe knit his ſervice to be at my Lords diſpoſing. And on the other ſide, I muſt and will ever acknowledge my Lords love, truſt and favour towards me, laſt of all his liberality, having infeofed me of land which I ſold for eighteen hundred pounds to Maſter <hi>Reynold Nicholas,</hi> and I think was more worth, and that at ſuch a time, and with ſo kind and noble circumſtances, as the manner was as much as the matter: which though it be but an idle digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, yet becauſe I am not willing to be ſhort in commemoration of his benefits, I will preſume to trouble your Lordſhip with the relating to you the manner of it. After the Queen had denied me the Solicitors place, for the which his Lordſhip had been a long and earneſt ſutor on my behalf, it pleaſed him to come to me from <hi>Richmond</hi> to <hi>Twicknam</hi> Park, and brake
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44030:3"/>
with me, and ſaid: Mr. <hi>Bacon,</hi> the Queen hath denied me the place for you, and hath placed another; I know you are the leaſt part of your own matter, but, you fare ill, becauſe you have choſen me for your mean and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance: you have ſpent your time and thoughts in my matters; I dye (theſe were his very words) if I do not ſomewhat towards your fortune, you ſhall not deny to accept a piece of Land, which I will beſtow upon you. My anſwer I remember was, that for my fortune it was no great matter: but that his Lordſhips offer made me call to mind what was wont to be ſaid when I was in <hi>France</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that he was the greateſt Uſurer in <hi>France,</hi> becauſe he had turned all his Eſtate into ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations; meaning that he had left himſelf nothing, but only had bound numbers of perſons to him. Now my Lord (ſaid I) I would not have you imitate his courſe, nor turn your ſtate thus by great gifts into obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, for you will find many bad debtors. He bad me take no care for that, and preſſed it: whereupon I ſaid, my Lord, I ſee I muſt be your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mager, and hold Land of your gift: but do you know the manner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing homage in law? Always it is with a ſaying of his faith to the King and his other Lords, and therefore my Lord (ſaid I) I can be no more yours than I was, and it may be with the ancient ſavings: and if I grow to be a rich man, you will give me leave to give it back to ſome of your unrewarded followers. But to return, ſure I am (though I can arrogate nothing to my ſelf but that I was a faithful remembrance to his Lordſhip) that while I had moſt credit with him his fortune went on beſt. And yet in two main points we always directly and contradictorily differed, which I will mention to your Lordſhip, becauſe it giveth light to all that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The one was, I ever ſet this down, that the only courſe to be held with the Queen, was by obſequiouſneſs and obſervance; and I remember would uſually engage confidently, that if he would take that courſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tly, and with choiſe of good particulars to expreſs it, the Queen would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> brought in time to <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> queſtion, to ask, <hi>What ſhould be done to the Man, that the King would honour:</hi> meaning, that her goodneſs was without limit, where there was a true concurrence, which I knew in her nature to be true. My Lord, on the otherſide, had a ſettled opinion, that the Queen could be brought to nothing, but by a kind of neceſſity and authority, and I well remember, when by violent courſes at any time he had get his will he would ask me. Now Sir: <hi>whoſe principles be true?</hi> And I would again ſay to him: <hi>My Lord, theſe courſes be like to hot waters, they will help at a pang: but if you uſe them, you ſhall ſpoil the ſtomack, and you ſhall be fain ſtill to make them ſtronger and ſtronger, and yet in the end they will leſs their operation:</hi> with much other variety, wherewith I uſed to touch that ſtring. Another point was, that I always vehemently diſſwaded him from ſeeking greatneſs by a military dependance, or by a popular dependance, as that which would breed in the Queen jealouſie, in himſelf preſumption, and in the State perturbation: and I did uſually compare them to <hi>Icarus</hi> two wings which were joyned on with wax, and would make him venture to ſoar too high, and then fall him at the height. And I would further ſay unto him: My Lord, ſtand upon two feet, and fly nor upon two wings. The two feet are the two kinds of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> Commutative and Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: uſe your greatneſs for advancing of merit and vertue and relieving wrongs and burdens, you ſhall need no other art or fineneſs: but he would
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44030:4"/>
tell me, that opinion came not from my mind, but from my robe. But it is very true, that I that never meant to inthral my ſelf to my Lord of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> nor any other man, more than ſtood with the publick good, did (though I could little prevail) divert him by all means poſſible from courſes of the wars and popularity: for I ſaw plainly the Queen muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther live or dye; if ſhe lived, then the times would be as in the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an old Prince; if ſhe died, the times would be as in the beginning of a new: and that if his Lordſhip did riſe too faſt in theſe courſes, the times might be dangerous for him, and he for them: Nay, I remember, I was thus plain with him, upon his voyage to the Iſlands, when I ſaw every Spring put forth ſuch actions of charge and provocation, that I ſaid to him, my Lord, when I came firſt unto you, I took you for a Phyſitian that deſired to cure the diſeaſes of the State; but now I doubt you will be like thoſe Phyſitians, which can be content to keep their Patients low, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would always be in requeſt: which plainneſs he nevertheleſs took very well, as he had an excellent ear, and was <hi>patientiſſimus veri,</hi> and aſſured me the caſe of the Realm required it: and I think this ſpeech of mine, and the like renewed afterwards, pricked him to write that Apology which is in many mens hands.</p>
            <p>But this difference in two points ſo main and material, bred in proceſs of time a diſcontinuance of privateneſs (as it is the manner of men ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to communicate where they think their courſes not approved) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Lordſhip and my ſelf; ſo as I was not called nor adviſed with for ſome year and a half before his Lordſhips going into <hi>Ireland,</hi> as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time: yet nevertheleſs, touching his going into <hi>Ireland,</hi> it pleaſed him expreſly, and in a ſet manner to deſire mine opinion and counſel. At which time I did not only diſſwade, but proteſt againſt his going, telling him with as much vehemency and aſſeveration as I could, that abſence in that kind would exulcerate the Queens mind, whereby it would not be poſſible for him to carry himſelf ſo, as to give her ſufficient contentment: nor for her to carry her ſelf ſo, as to give him ſufficient countenance, which would be ill for her, ill for him, and ill for the State. And becauſe I would omit no-argument, I remember I ſtood alſo upon the difficulty of the action: ſetting before him out of Hiſtories, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> was ſuch an enemy as the ancient <hi>Gauls,</hi> or <hi>Britons,</hi> or <hi>Germans</hi> were; &amp; that we ſaw how the <hi>Romans,</hi> who had ſuch diſcipline to govern their ſoldiers &amp; ſuch donatives to encourage them, and the whole world in a manner to levy them; yet when they came to deal with enemies which placed their felicity only in liberty, and the ſharpneſs of their ſword, and had the natural elemental advantages of woods, and boggs, and hardneſs of bodies, they ever found they had their hands full of them, and therefore concluded that going over with ſuch expectation as he did, and through the churliſhneſs of the enterpriſe not like to anſwer it, would mightily diminiſh his reputation; and many other reaſons I uſed, ſo as <hi>I</hi> am ſure I never in any thing in my life time dealt with him in like earneſtneſs by ſpeech, by writing, and by all the means I could deviſe. For I did as plainly ſee his overthrow chained, as it were by deſtiny to that journey, as it is poſſible for a man to ground a judgement upon future contingents. But my Lord, howſoever his ear was open, yet his heart and reſolution was ſhut againſt that adviſe, whereby his ruin might have been prevented. After my Lords going, I ſaw then
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44030:4"/>
how true a Prophet I was, in regard of the evident alteration which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſucceeded in the Queens mind; and thereupon I was ſtill in watch to find the beſt occaſion that in the weakneſs of my power I could either take or miniſter, to pull him out of the fire if it had been poſſible: and not long after, me thought I ſaw ſome overture thereof, which I apprehended readily; a particularity I think be known to very few, and the which I do the rather relate unto your Lordſhip, becauſe I hear it ſhould be talked, that while my Lord was in <hi>Ireland,</hi> I revealed ſome matters againſt him, or I cannot tell what; which if it were not a mear ſlander as the reſt is, but had any, though never ſo little colour, was ſurely upon this occaſion. The Queen one day at <hi>Noneſuch,</hi> a little (as I remember) before <hi>Cuffes</hi> coming over, I attending on her, ſhewed a paſſionare diſtaſt of my Lords proceedings in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as if they were unfortunate, without judgment, contemptuous, and not without ſome private end of his own, and all that might be, and was pleaſed, as ſhe ſpake of it to many that ſhe truſted leaſt, ſo to fall into the like ſpeech with me; whereupon I who was ſtill awake, and true to my grounds which I thought ſureſt for my Lords good, ſaid to this effect: Madam, I know not the particulars of Eſtate, and I know this that Princes actions muſt have no abrupt periods or concluſions, but otherwiſe I would think, that if you had my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> here with a white ſtaff in his hand, as my Lord of <hi>Leiceſter</hi> had, and continued him ſtill about you for ſociety to your ſelf and for an honor and ornament to your Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and Court in the eyes, of your people, and in the eyes of forraign Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors than were he in his right element: for, to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> content him as you do, and yet to put arms and power into his hands may be a kind of temptation to make him prove comberſome and unruly. And therefore if you would <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mp nere b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nam clauſulam,</hi> and ſend for him, and ſatisfie him with honour here near you, if your affairs which (as I have ſaid) I am not acquainted with, will permit it, I think were the beſt way. Which courſe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip knoweth, if it had been taken then all had been well, and no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt in my Lords coming over, nor continuance of theſe jealouſies, which that employment of <hi>Ireland</hi> bred, and my Lord here in his former great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Well, the next news that I heard, was that my Lord was come over, and that he was committed to his Chamber for leaving <hi>Ireland</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Queens licence: this was at <hi>Noneſuch,</hi> where (as my duty was) I came to his Lordſhip, and talked with him privately about a quarter of an hour, and he asked mine opinion of the courſe was taken with him; I told him: My Lord, <hi>Nubecula eſt, cito tranſibit:</hi> it is but a miſt: but ſhall I tell your Lordſhip, it is as miſts are if it go upwards, it may perhaps cauſe a ſnowre, if downwards it will clear up. And therefore good my Lord carry it ſo, as you take away by all means all umbrages and diſtaſts from the Queen, and eſpecially if I were worthy to adviſe you, (as I have been by your ſelf thought, and now your queſtion imports the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that opinion) obſerve three points: Firſt, make not this ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or peace, which is concluded with <hi>Tyrone,</hi> as a ſervice wherein you glory, but as a ſhuffling up of a proſecution which was not very fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. Next, repreſent not to the Queen any neceſſity of eſtate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as by a coercion or wrench, ſhe ſhould think her ſelf inforced to ſend you back into <hi>Ireland;</hi> but leave it to her. Thirdly, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck acceſſe <hi>impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, opportun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſeriouſly ſportingly every way. I remember my Lord was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44030:5"/>
willing to hear me, but ſpake very few words, and ſhaked his head ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, as if he thought I was in the wrong; but ſure I am, he did juſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in every one of theſe three points. After this, during the while ſince my Lord was committed to my Lord Keepers, I came divers times to the Queen, as I had uſed to do, about cauſes of her revenue and law bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, as is well known: by reaſon of which acceſſes, according to the ordinary charities of Court, it was given out, that I was one of them that incenſed the Queen againſt my Lord of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> Theſe ſpeeches I cannot tell, nor I will not think that they grew any way from her Majeſties own ſpeeches, whoſe memory I will ever honour: if they did, ſhe is with God, and <hi>miſerum est ab illis laedi, de quibus non poſſis queri.</hi> But I muſt give this teſtimony to my Lord <hi>Cecil,</hi> that one time in his houſe at the <hi>Savoy</hi> he dealt with me directly, and ſaid to me; Couſin, I hear it, but I believe it not, that you ſhould do ſome ill office to my Lord of <hi>Eſſex:</hi> for my part I am meerly paſſive and not active in this action, and I follow the Queen, and that heavi y, and I lead her not; my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> is one that in nature I could conſent with as well as with any one living; the Queen indeed is my Soveraign, and I am her creature, I may not loſe her, and the ſame courſe I would wiſh you to take: whereupon I ſatisfied him how far <hi>I</hi> was from any ſuch mind. And as ſometimes it cometh to paſs, that mens inclinations are opened more in a toy, than in a ſerious matter: A little before that time, being about the midle of <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Term, her Majeſty had a purpoſe to dine at my lodge at <hi>Twicknam</hi> Park, at which time <hi>I</hi> had (though <hi>I</hi> profeſs not to be a Poet) prepared a Sonnet directly tending and alluding to draw on her Majeſties reconcilement to my Lord, which <hi>I</hi> remember alſo, ſhewed to a great perſon, &amp; one of my Lords near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt friends, who commended it: this, though it be (as <hi>I</hi> ſaid) but a toy, yet it ſhewed plainly in what ſpirit <hi>I</hi> proceeded, and that <hi>I</hi> was ready not only to do my Lord good offices, but to publiſh and declare my ſelf for him; and never was ſo ambitious of any thing in my life time, as <hi>I</hi> was to have carried ſome token or favour from her Majeſty to my Lord, uſing all the art <hi>I</hi> had, both to procure her Majeſty to ſend, and my ſelf to be the meſſenger: for as to the former <hi>I</hi> feared not to alledge to her, that this proceeding toward my Lord, was a thing towards the people very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſible, and therefore wiſhed her Majeſty however ſhe did, yet to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge her ſelf of it, and lay it upon others; and therefore that ſhe ſhould intermix her proceeding with ſome immediate graces from her ſelf, that the world might take knowledge of her Princely nature and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, leſt it ſhould alienate the hearts of her people from her, which <hi>I</hi> did ſtand upon, knowing well that if ſhe once relented to ſend or viſit, thoſe demonſtrations would prove matter of ſubſtance for my Lords good. And to draw that employment upon my ſelf, <hi>I</hi> adviſed her Majeſty, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God ſhould move her to turn the light of her favours towards my Lord, to make ſignification to him thereof: that her Majeſty, if ſhe did it not in perſon, would at the leaſt uſe ſome ſuch mean as might not intitle themſelves to any part of the thanks, as perſons that were thought mighty with her to work her, or to bring her about; but to uſe ſome ſuch as could not be thought but a meer conduct of her own goodneſs: but <hi>I</hi> could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prevail with her, though <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded ſhe ſaw plainly whereat <hi>I</hi> levelled: but ſhe plainly had me in jealouſie, that <hi>I</hi> was not hers intirely,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44030:5"/>
but ſtill had inward and deep reſpects towards my Lord, more than ſtood at that time with her will and pleaſure. About the ſame time <hi>I</hi> remember an anſwer of mine in a matter which had ſome affinity with my Lords cauſe, which though it grew from me, went after about in others names. For her Majeſty being mightily incenſed with that Book which was dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> being a ſtory of the firſt year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, thinking it a ſeditious prelude to put into the peoples head boldneſs and faction, ſaid, She had an opinion, that there was treaſon in it, and asked me if I could not find any places in it, that might be drawn within caſe of treaſon: whereto I anſwered; for treaſon ſurely I found none, but for fellony very many. And when her Majeſty haſtily asked me wherein; I told her, the Author had committed, very apparent theft, for he had taken moſt of the ſentences of <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> and tranſlated them into Engliſh, and put them into his Text. And another time when the Queen would not be perſwaded, that it was his writing whoſe name was to it, but that it had ſome more miſchievous Author, and ſaid with great indignation, that ſhe would have him racked to produce his Author; I replyed, Nay, Madam, he is a Doctor, never rack his perſon, but rack his ſtile; let him have pen, ink, and paper, and help of books, and be enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to continue the Story where it breaketh off, and I will undertake by collecting the ſtiles, to judge whether he were the Author or no. But for the main matter, ſure I am, when the Queen at any time asked mine opinion of my Lords caſe, I ever in one tenor, ſaid unto her: that they were faults which the Law might term Contempts, becauſe they were the trangreſſion of her particular directions and inſtructions: but then what defence might be made of them, in regard of the great intereſt the perſon had in her Majeſties favour, in regard of the greatneſs of his place, and the ampleneſs of his Commiſſion; in regard of the nature of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs being action of war, which in common caſes cannot be tyed to ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of inſtructions, in regard of the diſtance of the place, having alſo a ſea between, that demands and commands; muſt be ſubject to wind and weather; in regard of a councel of State in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which he had at his back to avow his actions upon; and laſtly, in regard of a good intention that he would alledge for himſelf, which I told her in ſome religions was held to be a ſufficient diſpenſation for Gods commandements, much more for Princes. In all theſe regards, I beſought her Majeſty to be adviſed again and again, how ſhe brought the cauſe into any publick queſtion: nay, I went further, for I told her, my Lord was and eloquent and well ſpoken man, and beſides his eloquence of nature or art, he had an eloquence of accident which paſſed them both, which was the pity and benevolence of his hearers; and therefore that when he ſhould come to his anſwer for himſelf, I doubted his words would have ſo unequal paſſage above theirs that ſhould charge him, as would not be for her Majeſties honour; and therefore wiſhed the concluſion might be, that they might wrap it up pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately between themſelves, and that ſhe would reſtore my Lord to his former attendance, with ſome addition of honour to take away diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. But this I will never deny, that I did ſhew no approbation gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of his being ſent back again into <hi>Ireland,</hi> both becauſe it would have carried a repugnancy with my former diſcourſe, and becauſe I was in mine own heart fully perſwaded, that it was not good, neither for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44030:6"/>
Queen, nor for the State, nor for himſelf: and yet I did not diſſawde it neither, but left it ever as <hi>locus lubricus.</hi> For this particularity I do well remember that after your Lordſhip was named for the place in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and not long before your going, it pleaſed her Majeſty at <hi>White-hall</hi> to ſpeak to me of that nomination: at which time I ſaid to her: Surely, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, if you mean not to imploy my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> thither again, your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty cannot make a better choiſe, and was going on to ſhow ſome reaſon and her Majeſty interrupted me with great paſſion: <hi>Eſſex!</hi> (ſaid ſhe) when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I ſend <hi>Eſſex</hi> back again into <hi>Ireland,</hi> I will Marry you, claim it of me: whereunto I ſaid; Well, Madam, I will releaſe that contract if his going be for the good of your State. Immediately after the Queen had thought of a courſe (which was alſo executed) to have ſomewhat publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Star-chamber, for the ſatisfaction of the world touching my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his reſtraint, and my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> not to be called to it, but occaſion to be taken by reaſon of ſome Libels then diſperſed; which when her Majeſty propounded unto me, I was utterly againſt it; and told her plainly, that the people would ſay, that my Lord was wounded upon his back, and that juſtice had her balance taken from her, which ever conſiſted of an accuſation and defence, with many other quick and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant tearms to that purpoſe: inſomuch that I remember I ſaid, that my Lord <hi>in foro famae</hi> was too hard for her; and therefore wiſhed her as I had done before, to wrap it up privately. And certainly I offended her at that time, which was rare with me: for I call to mind that both the <hi>Christmas, Lent,</hi> and <hi>Easter</hi> Term following, though I came divers times to her upon Law buſineſs, yet me thought her face and manner was not ſo clear and open to me, as it was at the firſt. And ſhe did directly charge me, that I was abſent that day at the Star-chamber, which was very true; but I alledged ſome indiſpoſition of body to excuſe it: and during all the time aforeſaid, there was <hi>altum ſilentium</hi> from her to me touching my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> cauſes.</p>
            <p>But towards the end of <hi>Eaſter</hi> Term, her Majeſty brake with me, and told me that ſhe had found my words true, for that the proceeding in the Star-chamber had done no good, but rather kindled factious bruits (as ſhe termed them) than quenched them, and therefore that ſhe was determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned now for the ſatisfaction of the world, to proceed againſt my Lord in the Star-chamber by an information <hi>ore tenus,</hi> and to have my Lord brought to his anſwer: howbeit ſhe ſaid, ſhe would aſſure me that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhe did, ſhould be towards my Lord <hi>ad caſtigationem, &amp; non ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructionem,</hi> as indeed ſhe had often repeated the ſame phraſe before: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I ſaid (to the end utterly to divert her:) Madam, if you will have me ſpeak to you in this argument, I muſt ſpeak to you as Frier <hi>Bacons</hi> head ſpake, that ſaid firſt, <hi>Time is,</hi> and then, <hi>Time was,</hi> and <hi>Time would never be;</hi> for certainly (ſaid I) it is now far too late, the matter is cold, and hath taken too much wind; whereat ſhe ſeemed again offended, and roſe from me, and that reſolution for a while continued; and after, in the beginning of <hi>Midſummer</hi> Tearm, I attending her, and finding her ſettled in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution (which I heard of alſo otherwiſe) ſhe falling upon the like ſpeech, it is true, that ſeeing no other remedy, I ſaid to her ſlightly, Why, Madam, if you will needs have a proceeding, you were beſt have it in ſome ſuch ſort as <hi>Ovid</hi> ſpake of his Miſtreſs, <hi>Eſt aliquid luce patente minus,</hi> to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44030:6"/>
make a Counſel-table matter of it, and there an end; which ſpeech again ſhe ſeemed to take in ill part, but yet I think it did good at that time, and helped to divert that courſe of proceeding by information in the Star-chamber. Nevertheleſs, afterwards it pleas'd her to make a more ſolemn matter of the proceeding, and ſome few days after, when order was given that the matter ſhould be heard at <hi>York-houſe,</hi> before an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Councellers, Peers, and Judges, and ſome audience of men of quality to be admitted: and then did ſome principal Councellers ſend for us of the learned Councel, and notifie her Majeſties pleaſure unto us, ſave that it was ſaid to me openly by one of them, that her Majeſty was not yet reſolved whether ſhe would have me forborn in the buſineſs or no. And hereupon might ariſe that other ſiniſter and untrue ſpeech that I hear is raiſed of me, how I was a Suiter to be uſed againſt my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> at that time: for it is very true, that I that knew well what had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Queen and me, and what occaſion I had given her both of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſt and diſtruſt, in croſſing her diſpoſition, by ſtanding ſteadfaſtly for my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and ſuſpecting it alſo to be a ſtratagem ariſing from ſome particular emulation, I writ to her two or three words of complement, ſignifying to her Majeſty, that if ſhe would be pleaſed to ſpare me in my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> cauſe, out of the conſideration ſhe took of my obligation towards him, I ſhould reckon it for one of her greateſt favours: but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſiring her Majeſty to think that I knew the degrees of duties, and that no particular obligation whatſoever to any ſubject could ſupplant or weaken that entireneſs of duty that I did owe and bear to her and her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and this was the goodly ſuite I made, being a reſpect no man that had his wits could have omitted: but nevertheleſs I had a further reach in it, for I judged that days work would be a full period of any bitterneſs or harſhneſs between the Queen and my Lord, and therefore if I declared my ſelf fully according to her mind at that time, which could not do my Lord any manner of prejudice, I ſhould keep my credit with her ever after, whereby to do my Lord ſervice, Hereupon the next news that I heard, was, that we were all ſent for again, and that her Majeſties pleaſure was, we all ſhould have parts in the buſineſs; and the Lords falling into diſtribution of our parts, it was allotted to me, that I ſhould ſet forth ſome undutiful carriages of my Lord in giving occaſion and countenance to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Pamphlet, as it was termed, which was dedicated unto him, which was the Book before mentioned of King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. Whereupon I replyed to that allotment, and ſaid to their Lordſhips, that it was an old matter, and had no manner of coherence with the reſt of the Charge, being matters of <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp; therefore that I having been wronged by bruits before, this would expoſe me to them more; and it would be ſaid, I gave in evidence mine own tales. It was anſwered again with good ſhew, that becauſe it was conſidered how I ſtood tyed to my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> therefore that part was thought fitteſt for me, which did him leaſt hurt: for that whereas all the reſt was matter of Charge and Accuſation, this only was but matter of Caveat and Admonition. Wherewith though I was in mine one mind little ſatisfied, becauſe I knew well a man were better to be charged with ſome faults, than admoniſhed of ſome others: yet the concluſion binding upon the Queens pleaſure directly, <hi>volens nolens,</hi> I could not avoid that part that was laid upon me; which part if in the delivery I did handle not ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44030:7"/>
(though no man before me did in ſo clear tearms free my Lord from all diſloyalty as I did) that your Lordſhip knoweth, muſt be aſcribed to the ſuperiour duty I did owe to the Queens fame and honour in a publick proceeding, and partly to the intention I had to uphold my ſelf in credit and ſtrength with the Queen, the better to be able to do my Lord good offices afterwards: for as ſoon as this day was paſt, I loſt no time, but the very next day following (as I remember) I attended her Majeſty, fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to try and put in ure my utmoſt endeavour (ſo far as I in my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs could give furtherance) to bring my Lord again ſpeedily into Court and Favour, and knowing (as I ſuppoſed at leaſt) how the Queen was to be uſed, I thought that to make her conceive that the matter went well then, was the way to make her leave off there; and I remember well, I ſaid to her, you have now Madam obtained victory over two things, which the greateſt Princes in the world cannot at their wills ſubdue: the one is over Fame, the other is over a great Mind: for ſurely the world is now (I hope) reaſonably well ſatisfied; and for my Lord, he did ſhew that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation towards your Majeſty, as I am perſwaded he was never in his life time more fit for your favour than he is now: therefore if your Majeſty will not marr it by lingring, but give over at the beſt, and now you have made ſo good a full point, receive him again with tenderneſs, I ſhall then think that all that is paſt, is for the beſt. Whereat I remember ſhe took exceeding great contentment, and did often iterate and put me in mind, that ſhe had ever ſaid, that her proceedings ſhould be <hi>ad reparationem,</hi> and not <hi>ad ruinam,</hi> as who ſaith, that now was the time I ſhould well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that that ſaying of hers ſhould prove true. And further ſhe willed me to ſet down in writing all that paſſed that day. I obeyed her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and within ſome few days brought her again the narration, which I did read unto her at two ſeveral afternoons: and when I came to that part that ſet forth my Lords own anſwer, (which was my principal care) I do well bear in mind, that ſhe was extraordinarily moved with it, in kindneſs and relenting towards my Lord, and told me afterwards (ſpeaking how well I had expreſſed my Lords part) that ſhe perceived old love would not eaſily be forgotten: whereto I anſwered ſuddenly, that I hoped ſhe meant that by her ſelf. But in concluſion I did adviſe her, that now ſhe had taken a repreſentation of the matter to her ſelf, that ſhe would let it go no further: for, Madam, (ſaid I) the fire blazeth well al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, what ſhould you tumble it? and beſides it may pleaſe you keep to a convenience with your ſelf in this caſe: for ſince your expreſs direction was, there ſhould be no Regiſter nor Clarke to take this Sentence, nor no Record or Memorial made up of the Proceeding, why ſhould you now do that popularly, which you would not admit to be done judicially? Whereupon ſhe did agree, that that writing ſhould be ſuppreſſed, and I think there were not five perſons that ever ſaw it. But from this time forth during the whole latter end of that Summer, while the Court was at <hi>Nonſuch</hi> and <hi>Otlands,</hi> I made it my task and ſcope to take and give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions for my Lords reintegration in his fortune: which my intention I did alſo ſignifie to my Lord, aſſoon as ever he was at his liberty; whereby I might without peril of the Queens indignation write to him, and having received from his Lordſhip a courteous and loving acception of my good will and indeavours, I did apply it in all my acceſſes to the Queen, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44030:7"/>
were very many at that time, and purpoſely ſought and wrought upon other variable pretences, but only and chiefly for that purpoſe. And on the otherſide, I did not forbear to give my Lord from time to time faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful advertiſement what I found, and what I wiſhed. And I drew for him by his appointment ſome letters to her Majeſty, which though I knew well his Lordſhips gift and ſtile was far better than mine own, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he required it, alledging that by his long reſtraint he was grown al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a ſtranger to the Queens preſent conceipts, I was ready to perform it: and ſure I am, that for the ſpace of ſix weeks, or two months it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered ſo well, as I expected continually his reſtoring to his attendance. And I was never better welcome to the Queen, nor more made of, than when I ſpake fulleſt and boldeſt for him: in which kind the particulars were exceeding many, whereof for an example I will remember to your Lordſhip one or two, as at one time I call to mind, her Majeſty was ſpeaking of a Fellow that undertook to Cure, or at leaſt to Eaſe my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Gout, and asked me how it went forward; and I told her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that at the firſt he received good by it, but after in the courſe of his Cure he found himſelf at a ſtay or rather worſe: the Queen ſaid again, I will tell you <hi>Bacon</hi> the errour of it; the manner of theſe Phyſitians, and eſpecially theſe Empericks, is to continue one kind of Medicine, which at the firſt is proper, being to draw out the ill humor, but after they have not the diſcretion to change their Medicine, but apply ſtill drawing Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, when they ſhould rather intend to cure and corroborate the part. Good Lord, Madam, (ſaid I) how wiſely and aptly can you ſpeak, and diſcern of Phyſick miniſtred to the body, and conſider not that there is the like occaſion of Phyſick miniſtred to the mind: as now in the caſe of my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> your Princely word ever was, that you intended ever to reform his mind, and not ruin his fortune: I know well you cannot but think that you have drawn the humor ſufficiently, and therefore it were more than time, and it were but for doubt of mortifying or exulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, that you did apply and miniſter ſtrength and comfort unto him: for theſe ſame gradations of yours are fitter to corrupt than correct any mind of greatneſs, And another time I remember ſhe told me for news, that my Lord had written unto, her ſome very dutiful Letters, and that ſhe had been moved by them, and when ſhe took it to be the abundance of the heart, ſhe found it to be but a preparative to a ſuit for the renuing of his Farm of ſweet Wines: whereunto I replyed; O Madam, how doth your Majeſty conſtrue theſe things, as if theſe two could not ſtand well together, which indeed nature hath planted in all creatures. For there are but two ſympathies, the one towards <hi>Perfection,</hi> the other towards <hi>Preſervation</hi> That to Perfection, as the Iron contendeth to the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: that to Preſervation, as the Vine will creep towards a ſtake or prop that ſtands by it, not for any love to the ſtake, but to uphold it ſelf. And therefore, Madam, you muſt diſtinguiſh my Lords deſire to do you ſervice, is as to his perfection, that which he thinks himſelf to be born for: whereas his deſire to obtain this thing of you, is but for a ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And not to trouble your Lordſhip with many other particulars like unto theſe, it was at the ſelf ſame time that I did draw with my Lords privity, and by his appointment, two letters, the one written as from my Brother, the other as an anſwer returned from my Lord, both to be by me
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44030:8"/>
in ſecret manner ſhewed to the Queen, which it pleaſed my Lord very ſtrangely to mention at the Bar: the ſcope of which were but to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and picture forth unto her Majeſty my Lords mind to be ſuch, as I knew her Majeſty would faineſt have had it, which letters whoſoever ſhall ſee, (for they cannot now be retracted or altered, being by reaſon of my Brothers, or his Lordſhips ſervants delivery, long ſince come into divers hands) let him judge, eſpecially if he knew the Queen, and do remember thoſe times, whether they were not the labours of one that ſought to bring the Queen about for my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his good. The troth is that the iſſue of all his dealing grew to this, that the Queen by ſome ſlackneſs of my Lords, as I imagine, liked him worſe and worſe, and grew more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed towards him. Then, ſhe remembring belike the continual, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant, and confident ſpeeches and courſes that I had held on my Lords ſide, became utterly alienated from me, and for the ſpace of (at leaſt) three months, which was between <hi>Michaelmas</hi> and <hi>New-years-tide</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, would not ſo much as look on me, but turned away from me with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and purpoſe-like diſcountenance whereſoever ſhe ſaw me: and at ſuch time as I deſired to ſpeak with her about Law-buſineſs, ever ſent me forth very ſlight refuſals, inſomuch as it is moſt true, that immediately after <hi>New-years tide</hi> I deſired to ſpeak with her; and being admitted to her, I dealt with her plainly, and ſaid: Madam, I ſee you withdraw your favour from me, and now I have loſt many friends for your ſake, I ſhall loſe you too: you have put me like one of thoſe that the French-men call <hi>Enfans perdus,</hi> that ſerve on foot before horſemen, ſo have you put me into matters of envy without place, or without ſtrength: and I know at Cheſs a pawn before the King, is ever much plaid upon: a great many love me not, becauſe they think I have been againſt my Lord of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> and you love me not, becauſe you know I have been for him: yet will I never repent me, that I have dealt in ſimplicity of heart towards you both, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of cautions to my ſelf: and therefore <hi>vivus videnſque pereo.</hi> If I do break my neck, I ſhall do it in a manner as Maſter <hi>Dorrington</hi> did it, which walked on the Battlements of the Church many days, and took a view and ſurvey where he ſhould fall: and ſo, Madam, (ſaid I) I am not ſo ſimple, but that I take a proſpect of mine overthrow, only I thought I would tell you ſo much, that you may know that it was faith, and not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that brought me into it, and ſo <hi>I</hi> will pray for you. Upon which ſpeeches of mine uttered with ſome paſſion, it is true her Majeſty was exceedingly moved; and accumulated a number of kind and gracious words upon me, and willed me to reſt upon this, <hi>Gratia mea ſufficit,</hi> and a number of other ſenſible and tender words and demonſtrarions, ſuch as more could not be; but as touching my Lord of <hi>Eſſex, ne verbum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi> Whereupon I departed, reſting then determined to meddle no more in the matter; as that, that I ſaw would overthrow me, and not be able to do him any good. And thus I made mine own peace with mine own confidence at that time; and this was the laſt time I ſaw her Majeſty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eight of <hi>February,</hi> which was the day of my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his misfortune, after which time, for that I performed at the Bar in my pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſervice, your Lordſhip knoweth by the rules of duty, that I was to do it honeſtly, and without prevarication: but for any putting my ſelf into it, I proteſt before God, I never moved either the Queen, or the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44030:8"/>
living concerning my being uſed in the ſervice, either of evidence or examination: but it was meerly laid upon me with the reſt of my fellows. And for the time which paſſed, I mean between the arraignment and my Lords ſuffering, I well remember I was but once with the Queen, at what time though I durſt not deal directly for my Lord as things then ſtood; yet generally I did both commend her Majeſties mercy, terming it to her as an excellent balm that did continually diſtill from her Soveraign hands, and made an excellent odour in the ſenſes of her people: and not only ſo, but I took hardneſs to extenuate, not the fact, for that I durſt not; but the danger, telling her that if ſome baſe or cruel minded perſons had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into ſuch an action, it might have cauſed much blood and combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but it appeared well they were ſuch as knew not how to play the Malefactors, and ſome other words which I now omit. And as for the reſt of the carriage of my ſelf in that ſervice, I have many honorable witneſſes that can tell, that the next day after my Lords arraignment, by my diligence and information touching the quality and nature of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors, ſix of nine were ſtayed, which otherwiſe had been attainted, I bringing their Lordſhips letter for their ſtay, after the Jury was ſworn to paſs upon them; ſo near it went: and how careful I was, and made it my part, that whoſoever was in trouble about that matter, aſſoon as ever his caſe was ſufficiently known and defined of, might not continue in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, but be ſet at liberty: and many other parts, which I am well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſtood with the duty of an honeſt man. But indeed I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for the caſe of Sir <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> the Queen demanding my opinion of it, I told her, I thought it was as hard as many of the reſt: but what was the reaſon? becauſe at that time I had ſeen only his accuſation, and had never been preſent at any examination of his: and the matter ſo ſtanding, I had been very untrue to my ſervice, if I had not delivered that opinion. But afterwards upon a re-examination of ſome that charged him, who weakned their own teſtimony; and eſpecially hearing himſelf <hi>viva voce,</hi> I went inſtantly to the Queen out of the ſoundneſs of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and not regarding what opinion I had formerly delivered, told her Majeſty, I was ſatified and reſolved in my conſcience, that for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the action, the plot was to countenance the action further by him in reſpect of his place, than they had indeed any intereſt or intelligence with him. It is very true alſo, about that time her Majeſty taking a liking of my Pen, upon that which I had done before concerning the proceeding at <hi>York-houſe,</hi> and likewiſe upon ſome other declarations, which in former times by her appointment I put in writing, commanded me to pen that book, which was publiſhed for the better ſatisfaction of the world: which I did but ſo, as never Secretary had more particular, and expreſs directions and inſtructions in every point how to guide my hand in it: and not only ſo, but after that I had made a firſt draught thereof and propounded it to certain principal Councellors, by her Majeſties appointment, it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, weighed, cenſured, altered, and made almoſt anew, writing accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Lordſhips better conſideration: wherein their Lordſhips and my ſelf both were as religious and curious of truth, as deſirous of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: and my ſelf indeed gave only words and form of ſtile in purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their direction. And after it had paſſed their allowance, it was again ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly peruſed by the Queen her ſelf, and ſome alterations made again by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44030:9"/>
her appointment: nay, and after it was ſet to print, the Queen, who as your Lordſhip knoweth, as ſhe was excellent in great matters, ſo ſhe was exquiſite in ſmall: and noted that I could not forget my ancient reſpect to my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> in terming him ever my Lord of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> almoſt in every page of the Book, which ſhe thought not fit, but would have it made, <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or the late Earl of <hi>Eſſex:</hi> whereupon of force it was printed <hi>de novo,</hi> and the firſt copies ſuppreſſed by her peremptory commandment. And this my good Lord, to my furtheſt remembrance, is all that paſſed wherein I had part, which I have ſet down as near as I could in the very words and ſpeeches that were uſed, not becauſe they are worthy the repetition, I mean thoſe of mine own; but to the end your Lordſhip may lively and plainly diſcern between the face of truth, and a ſmooth tale. And the rather alſo, becauſe in things that paſſed a good while ſince, the very words and phraſes did ſometimes bring to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance the matters, wherein I report me to your honorable judgement, whether you do not ſee the traces of an honeſt man: and had I been as well believed either by the Queen or by my Lord, as I was well heard by them both, both my Lord had been fortunate, and ſo had my ſelf in his fortune.</p>
            <p>To conclude therefore, I humbly pray your Lordſhip to pardon me for troubling you with this long Narration, and that you will vouchſafe to hold me in your good opinion, till you know I have deſerved, or finde that I ſhall deſerve the contrary; and even ſo I continue,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>At your Lordſhips Honourable commandments very humbly.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44030:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
